Guide to the John James Audubon Print Collection [1820]-1860, 1985 PR 162
New-York Historical Society
John James Audubon print collection
[1820]-1860, 1985 (bulk 1832-1845)
New-York Historical Society
Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
PR 162
1.88 Linear feet (2 boxes, 1 drawer)
The Audubon print collection contains hand-colored aquatints, lithographs, chromolithographs, and items of ephemera of or pertaining to the work of John James Audubon, including both original prints from his famous color-plate books of natural history, and later, derivative prints of the same.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series.
Missing Title
Series I. Birds of America
Series II. Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America
Series III. Miscellaneous
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection is mainly comprised of gifts from a variety of donors. The proof prints were purchased in 1947.
Related Materials
Portraits of John James Audubon and his family can be found in the Portrait File (PR 052). The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections also holds a double Elephant folio set of Audubon's Birds of America, and the N-YHS Library has an Octavo set of the same. The Manuscripts Department holds some of Audubon's correspondence. The N-YHS Museum holds Audubon's original watercolors for Birds of America, as well as other work by Audubon, including an empty marbleized paper and leather portfolio, of double Elephant folio size, with "Birds of America" printed on the cover, which was used by Audubon himself to carry his watercolors or sample prints as samples to show to potential subscribers.
Scope and Contents
The John James Audubon Print Collection spans the period from ca. 1827-1860, and 1977 to 1986 and contains both original prints from Audubon's famous color-plate books of natural history, and later derivatives. The collection is divided into three series: Birds of America;Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America; and Miscellaneous.
Aquatints (prints); Chromolithographs.; Circulars (fliers); Ephemera.; Lithographs.; Proofs.; Visiting cards.; Birds -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Natural history -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Prints -- Coloring.; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851 -- Birds of America.; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851 -- Viviparous quadrupeds of North America.; Havell, Robert, 1793-1878; Childs & Inman
- Series I: Birds of America
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Birds of America contains material related to the original double Elephant folio publication of Birds of America, published in numbers from 1827 to 1838. Plates for this edition were aquatinted by Robert Havell, Jr., after drawings by Audubon, and were hand-colored both by Havell's studio staff and Audubon's wife and children. This series is arranged into three subseries: Pattern Proof Prints, Loose Plates, and Facsimiles and Reproductions.
  The fifteen color proof prints were used as patterns for the colorists of the aquatints. These sheets give primary and detailed evidence about the coloring process; several have penciled color notations, and one has a notation for textual change. Eleven loose plates from the double Elephant Folio edition, all marked with Havell's name, are also included. One of these, the White-headed Eagle, appears in both uncolored and colored format. Several modern reprints of Audubon's birds can also be found in this series.
  Prints are arranged by plate number, where known.
  - Pattern Proof Prints
    - Common Yellow Throat [Plate 24], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Kentucky Warbler [Plate 38], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Chestnut Sided Warbler [Plate 59], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Autumnal Warbler [Plate 88], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Carolina Titmouse [Plate 160], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Orange Crowned Warbler [Plate 178], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Tree Sparrow [Plate 188], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Manx Shearwater [Plate 295], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Yellow Breasted Rail [Plate 329], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - American Widgeon [Plate 345], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Rocky Mountain Plover [Plate 350], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Lapland Longspur [Plate 365], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Golden Winged Warbler [Plate 414], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Tawny Thrush/Townsend's Thrush & Canada Jay [Plate 419], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Western Duck [Plate 429], 1827-1838 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Loose Plates
    These prints are housed flat in a map case.
    - White-headed Eagle [Plate 31], 1828 (Folder FF 1)
    - House Wren [Plate 83], undated (Folder FF 1)
    - Connecticut Warbler [Plate 138], 1832 (Folder FF 1)
    - Sooty Tern [Plate 235], 1834 (Folder FF 1)
    - Great Marbled Godwit [Plate 238], 1835 (Folder FF 1)
    - Red-necked Grebe [Plate 298], 1836 (Folder FF 1)
    - Tell-tale Godwit or Snipe [Plate 308], 1836 (Folder FF 1)
    - Redheaded Duck [Plate 322], 1836 (Folder FF 1)
    - Trumpeter Swan [Plate 376], 1837 (Folder FF 1)
  - Facsimiles and Reproductions
    - Great Egret, 1977 (Folder FF 2)
      General note
      Printed by the National Audubon Society
    - Canvas Backed Duck, undated (Folder FF 2)
      Printed by R. R. Donnelley & Sons, courtesy of the Field Museum of Natural History
    - American White Pelican, 1985 (Folder FF 2)
      No. 152 of 500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
    - Wild Turkey, 1985 (Folder FF 2)
      No. 135 of 500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
    - Purple Heron, 1985 (Folder FF 2)
    - Brown Pelican, 1985 (Folder FF 2)
      No. 1136 of 1500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
- Series II: Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America
  Series II. Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America was issued from 1845 to 1848. Six loose plates of small animals from that book are held here. All are hand colored lithographs by J. T. Bowen after drawings by John James Audubon.
  - Common American Wildcat [Plate 1], 1842 (Folder FF 3)
  - Cat Squirrel [Plate 17], 1843 (Folder FF 3)
  - Red-tailed Squirrel [Plate 55], 1844 (Folder FF 3)
  - Brindled Weasel [Plate 60], 1845 (Folder FF 3)
  - Brewer's Shrew Mole [Plate 74], 1845 (Folder FF 3)
  - Carolina Shrew [Plate 75], 1845 (Folder FF 3)
- Series III: Miscellaneous
  Series III contains nineteenth century material that does not readily fit into the above two series. A lithograph of a "Marsh Hen," by the firm Childs and Inman of Philadelphia and published in 1832, is one of a very few known copies of this print; the only one of Audubon's birds to be separately printed in this format. Little documentary evidence exists of Audubon's foray into lithography, but the print is thought to have been drawn on stone by Albert Newsam in the summer of 1832.
  Included in this series are four of John James Audubon's calling cards; all but one note his distinction as a "Fellow of the Royal Linnean Societies of London." A prospectus dated June 1834 announces the forthcoming publication of the double Elephant folio of Birds of America, and seeks subscribers. The series also includes a title page from and another prospectus for the 1860 double Elephant size reissue of Birds of America, with chromolithography by J. Bien, which was published by Roe, Lockwood, and Son, of New York.
  - Marsh Hen [no plate marking], 1832 (Folder FF 4)
    Lithograph, drawn and printed by Childs and Inman, Philadelphia
  - Title Page from Birds of America, edition of 1860, published in New York by Roe, Lockwood & Son, New York, chromolithography by J. Bien (Folder FF 5)
  - John James Audubon, four calling cards, three as "Fellow of the Royal Linnean Societies of London", [1820-1839] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brochure advertising double Elephant Folio edition of Audubon's Birds of America, 1834 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brochure advertising double Elephant Folio and Octavo chromolithography editions of Audubon's Birds of America and Viviparous Quadrupeds, as well as a stand on which to display the book. Published by George Lockwood, 812 Broadway, New York., [1860] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)